Guide to the Horace Waller Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Horace Waller Papers
1858-1896
RG 72
Yale University Divinity School Library
1
(2 boxes)
The papers supplement and provide supporting detail for the major collection of Waller papers located at Rhodes House Library in Oxford, England. These papers document the Zambezi expedition of David Livingstone (1813-1873) and the early history of the Universities' Mission to Central Africa. Waller's friendship with Livingstone is apparent in their correspondence. Waller's deep interest in Africa and the problem of slavery continued throughout his life and is reflected in the diaries dated 1875-1876 during his rectorate at Twywell. Horace Waller was born in London in 1833. He went to Africa in 1861 as Lay Superintendent of the Universities' Mission to Central Africa. He resigned from the Mission in 1863 following a disagreement related to liberated slaves under the care of the Mission. In 1864, Waller returned to England. He became a member of the committee of the Anti-Slavery Society. He edited David Livingstone's journals for publication. He served as rector of Twywell, Thrapston, Northamptonshire from 1874 to 1895. Horace Waller died at East Liss, Hampshire in 1896.
Waller, Horace, 1833-1896
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
These items were purchased by the Library in 1983; they had been in the possession of Mrs. A.L. Baldwin, adopted daughter of Horace Waller's son. They supplement and provide supporting detail for the major collection of Waller papers located at Rhodes House Library in Oxford, England.
Biographical / Historical
1833 Born in London. Following his education, joined his father in business on the Stock Exchange
1861 Went to Africa as Lay Superintendent of Universities' Mission to Central Africa under leadership of Bishop Charles F. Mackenzie
1863 Resigned position with the Universities' Mission following disagreement with Bishop T.G. Tozer, Mackenzie's successor, regarding liberated slaves who had been under care of the Mission
1864 Returned to England
1867 Licensed to curacy of St. John's Chatham
1870 Became member of the committee of the Anti-Slavery Society Appointed vicar of Leytonstone,Essex
1874 Edited journals of David Livingstone for publication
1874-1895 Rector of Twywell, Thrapston, Northamptonshire
1896 Died at East Liss, Hampshire
Publications
1888 On Some African Entanglements of Great Britain
1890 Nyassaland: Great Britain's Case Against Portugal
1891 Ivory, Apes, and Peacocks: an African Contemplation
1893 Health Hints for Central Africa
1894 Slaving and Slavery in our British Protectorates, Nyssaland and Zanzibar
1896 The Case of Our Zanzibar Slaves: Why Not Liberate Them?
Scope and Contents
The papers of Horace Waller are a prime source of information regarding the Zambezi expedition of David Livingstone and the early history of the Universities' Mission to Central Africa. Livingstone and Waller corresponded frequently and had much confidence in each other. Waller wrote to his mother in 1863 regarding Livingstone: "I daresay you will see something of him if he goes home. He and I are and always have been so intimate I feel sure he would feel a great pleasure in telling you all about this poor tortured land.''(Letter of 1863 Jul 16 Box 1 Folder 8) This manuscript group includes five letters from Waller to Livingstone and one letter and one note written by Livingstone to Waller. Letters written by Waller to his family during the period 1861 to 1864 describe in detail his experiences in Africa and the controversies surrounding the location and policies of the Universities' Mission. Waller's deep interest in Africa and the problem of slavery continued throughout his life and is reflected in the diaries for 1875 and 1876 which are contained in this manuscript group.
The correspondence of Series I includes twenty-one letters or fragments of letters written by Waller to his family and ten letters to or from others. The letter and note from David Livingstone are of particular interest because they are not among those listed in David Livingstone: a Catalogue of Documents, compiled by G.W. Clendennen and I.C. Cunningham. Summaries of the contents of the letters in this manuscript group are contained in a description of the collection provided by the dealer from whom they were purchased. (See Box 2, following folder 25.)
Series II contains a variety of manuscript and printed writings: a list written by Waller during his school days, a pencilled journal possibly written by Waller's brother which describes travels through South Africa, Waller's diaries for the years 1875 and 1876, a small book published by Waller in 1891, and an article written about Waller following his death in 1896.
Series III contains four photographs. Dates and identification have been noted as available. The identification of the individual standing by a coffin in one of these photographs has been supplied on the basis of a similar photograph found in Donald Simpson's work Dark Companions.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence, 1861-1873
II. Diaries, writings, 1858 -1896
III. Photographs, 1864, 1874, n.d.
Missions -- Africa; Missions; Slavery; Africa -- History; Missionaries; Livingstone, David, 1813-1873; Waller, Horace, 1833-1896; Universities' Mission to Central Africa
- Correspondence, 1861-1873; Series I
  Existence and Location of Copies
  Digital copies of selected correspondence are available.
  - Correspondence to Family
    - ALS to father, 1861 May 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - ALS to father, 1861 May 8 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - ALS to parents, 1861 Oct 20 Nov 12 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - AL to mother, 1862 Nov 7 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - AL to father, 1862 Nov 22 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - AL to parents, 1863 Jan 25 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - AL to father, 1863 Feb 21 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - AL to mother, 1863 Feb 23 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - AL to mother, 1863 Mar 22 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - ALS to brother Gerald, 1863 Mar 29 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Addition to letter to mother, 1863 Apr 11 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - AL to father, 1863 Jun 29 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - ALS to brother and sister, 1863 Jul 13 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - AL to mother, 1863 Jul 16 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - ALS to father, 1863 Sep 11 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - AL to mother, 1863 Oct 10 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - AL to parents, 1863 Nov 16 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - AL to father, 1863 Dec 9 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - AL to parents, 1864 Jan 9 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - AL to Alice (wife), 1882 or 1883? (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - AL postscript, n.d.
  - Correspondence with Others
    - AL to J.G.R. Strong, 1861 Dec 14 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - AL to Dr. Mellor (Charles James Mellor) with dried plants enclosed, 1862 Jan 3 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - ALS to Mr. Joseph, 1862 Sep 6 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - ANS from David Livingstone, 1863 Jun 12 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - ALS from David Livingstone, 1864(?) Apr 2 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - ALS to David Livingstone, 1866 Nov 20 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - AL to David Livingstone, 1869 Dec 23 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - ALS to David Livingstone, 1870 Feb 17 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - ALS to David Livingstone, 1872 Feb 5 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - ALS to David Livingstone, 1873 Aug 27 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Diaries, Writings, 1858 -1896; Series II
  - AMs list of items collected at Braingorton, 1858 Aug 29 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Journal, 1864 Jun 2-29 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Diary, 1875 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Diary, 1876 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Book: Ivory, Apes and Peacocks by H. Waller, 1891 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Issue of Central Africa, monthly record of the work of the Universities' Mission, including article "In Memoriam Horace Waller", 1896 Apr (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Photographs, 1864, 1874, n.d.; Series III
  - Waller with six liberated slaves, 1864 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Jacob Wainwright with Livingstone's coffin (?), 1874(?) (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Chuma and Susi (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Waller in later years, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Description of collection provided by dealer (Box 2, Folder 26)